[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software so why can't our show
about reactive spring this is C Bob wolf
and I'm sitting here with fear in hollow
and he is from Austria and the lead
engineer of the spring framework pretty
much from the very beginning and I'm
happy to meet him here at go to con MCM
what we are going to talk about is how
reactive programming will be integrated
into the spring framework M and Jurgen
well welcome to the show first of all
thanks happy to have the opportunity and
one of the things that I understand is
that all the code that goes into the
framework has to be organized so I was
wondering what that actually means well
I have a certain tendency to growth well
source codes and just polish it so I my
own term where it is actually polishing
it's just my process of revisiting
certain parts of the code base
contributions to the core framework code
base and to fine-tune them both in terms
of source code style and in terms of the
actual implementation so I pay a lot of
attention not only to the style although
I do remove spaces and I do a line
Javadoc I do all those things but I in
particular pay attention to the
efficiency of the implementation reuse
of State for example optimize concurrent
access to shared state that sort of
attention to the detail is what what
others have have coined the term for and
they call it organized because I really
tend to do it
to pretty much all the code in the code
base whether it's originated with myself
or whether it was an external
contribution from within the team or
outside the team I do it basically -
everybody's code I guess that's part of
the meaning as well can you say a few
words about spring and what springs
goals are I guess quite a few listeners
are familiar with it but still maybe
someone didn't really use it so far I
suppose so but in all brevity spring as
in application framework has the
ambition of providing a
a comprehensive programming model for
the challenges in java application
development today of course today's is
actually a ongoing kind of today we pay
a lot of attention to evolve the
framework towards where the challenges
are and the challenges will be in java
programming so we are usually very
forward-looking the application
framework itself has quite some history
in the meantime dates back to 2002 2003
and its origins but at the same time it
is a very up-to-date very 2016 era
framework and it's in particular this
evolution and the depth ability of the
framework towards modern-day challenges
that we are most proud of Springs
through the ecosystems there are quite a
few other frameworks and tools too one
of the more recent words is spring boot
and it seems to be one of the tools that
is most popular right now so can you say
a few words about that and what it
actually is indeed the the ecosystem is
actually quite extensive in the mean
time and a spring boot is just a great
entry point into the ecosystem so it
spring dude is actually quite a few
things it is a kind of entry point in
terms of dependency management as well
you start with a particular spring boot
version you get pre chosen versions of
the core framework of spring data of
several other spring projects and
external third-party projects selected
for you and spring boot just brings them
in in a pre-tested pre integrated form
but it's one of its merits but at the
heart of the boot effort is an auto
configuration framework so boot
basically is an auto config story where
with very minimal configuration even
zero configuration you just get started
with spring web applications in
particular but also other kinds of
spring apps in a very minimal form a
third angle is the notion of embedded
bootstrapping and kind of special
deployment arrangements like fetch our
deployment where spring boot just has a
sweet spot in how it allows you to
deploy and and start your your spring
application in rather non-traditional
ways and this is where it connects
really nicely with the micro services
idea the microservices architecture
spring boot that at the heart of what it
does is not really a micro services
framework in in in any kind of
particularly a narrow sense but it turns
out to be a very fine match with what
microservices architectures demand both
in terms of the deployment of smaller
units and in terms of the auto
configuration effort where if you have
several deployments in mind each of them
might have its particular external
services to integrate with and spring
boots management of of the particular
dependencies of each of those deployment
units is also a sweet spot so spring a
spring boot is many things to many
people but it turns out to be a very
very popular part of the modern day
spring ecosystem the other part about
ours but is reactive programming of
course we already did a show about
reactive programming with wall Vallon
it's episode 249 but to get us started
here can you say a few words about what
reactive is in your opinion from my
perspective reactive is a very
overloaded term depending on who you ask
you can actually get quite different
impressions but from my own perspective
and from from our kind of spring
oriented perspective reactive is an
infrastructural challenge our modern-day
infrastructure is actually very capable
of the efficient use of resources at
runtime however we need to allow it to
actually operate efficiently our
programming models tend to just make
assumptions about the use of resources
that prevent the random infrastructure
from managing them efficiently it starts
with threats where our programming
models tend to just basically occupy
threats do its work as long as it takes
even with external calls to external
systems data stores and other
collaborating systems and at some point
released a thread when you're done
processing your current requests
this is actually a very
resource-intensive arrangement you have
to have a thread pool actually allowing
for such long-running request processing
on any given thread reactive basically
returns the idea around and suggests
programming models
where your processing algorithm is being
specified in the form of callbacks
allowing the runtime to call you back
when the resources actually allow for
for processing when the streams are
actually allowed for reading when you
out your output arrangement actually
allows for streaming output data back so
you're not you're you're not making
assumptions about always being able to
talk to your resources you react to your
to the availability of your resources
both on the incoming end and on the
outgoing in so it's from my perspective
it's it is primarily driven from this
infrastructural needs and some of the
technologies out there like the
low-level technologies are very very
capable of of allowing us to do this the
shortcomings are rather at the
programming model levels so this is not
a transparent upgrade underneath the
covers and every everything just
magically happens it really requires us
as application developers to rethink the
way that we are going about some of our
processing arrangements we need to
reconsider in particular web endpoint
arrangements HTTP request processing
arrangements to some degree data so axis
in general the use of transactions there
are many implications that follow from
this at the core what you're saying is
that if an HTTP request comes in the old
model would just take a thread and block
it forever while with reactive model and
HTTP requests or even multiple hvp
requests would be handled by one thread
if they enter the system or if new data
from data store comes in then the system
would react and that single thread would
handle all of those requests so how do
you develop reactive applications in
Java we are all pretty familiar with the
software model I guess and all the other
models where you would just get a
request that comes in and do your stuff
in a linear fashion if you look at what
you just said then we would need to have
something to react to data coming in
from the database the an HTTP request
that comes in and so on so what's the
impact on the programming model
I guess the easiest way to illustrate
this is actually the common examples out
there in for example our Irish Java
where the idea is to have certain common
operators like say map let map
operations that allow you to express
processing arrangements for four pieces
of incoming data as they come in as a
very close relationship of course to the
ability to nicely craft callbacks so
Java eight lenders of course are a
really nice fit the entire programming
model suggested by Eric's Java Co really
works much better on Java eight and it
ever did before it does not change the
fundamental arrangement though you are
being called back by a thread chosen by
the runtime for processing a particular
piece of data that just came in or that
is about to be written so you cannot
make any assumptions about the state of
the threat you can't just set up for
locals or have ongoing transactions
carried over as you maybe thought you
could do based on the heritage of the
several programming model this is a
situation where there are benefits to
each of the models though so it's not a
just a step forward in their in in every
possible sense the the transactional
model that were used to work with does
make a lot of sense for certain kinds of
applications where whereas reactive
programming basically requires you to
drop the entire notion of long-running
transactions you you interact with
resources in very short small steps and
you're going to be eventually consistent
at some point but you can't just have
transactions of several seconds
providing those consistency guarantees
to you anymore the reactive programming
model landscape in Java is very diverse
so there's a lot of things not just
rxjava out there there are very distinct
approaches like the actor model Anaka
there's vertex there are a plenty of
framework architectures that are really
suggesting a reactive model all the way
through where as our perspective is a
little bit more balanced we actually
look at the space from a more pragmatic
angle and the experience level of a Java
Rose spring development team is a very
important factor in its own right
reactive programming can be
uncomfortable it can even be sort of
messy to summarize at least so he it is
a different way to tackle a particular
problem space with implications that are
not necessarily of everybody's taste you
said that there are some issues around
transactions and reactive can you
elaborate on that I mean when I get in
an HTTP request and I do some work on
the database and then again I do some
work on the database this seems to be
something that I should really
encapsulate am on transaction if I have
several different parts of stuff that is
done on the database at least for
relational databases so would you say
that this is not the case anymore for
reactive applications or what's your
point there I would argue it is not a
fit for the fundamental idea of using a
resources just within a short call back
programming reactively at the entry
point level and then going down to the
data store asking the data store to have
a connection reserved for you kind of
goes against the grain it doesn't really
work aligned with the thread pool
management so from my perspective it
needs to be efficient all the way
through
you need to have efficient use of your
thread pool you need to have equally
efficient use of your resource pool your
connection pool underneath so you might
be forced because of some external
constraints of the external data store
not allowing you to interact any other
way you might be forced to do it in some
cases of some corners of your system in
a reactive world you typically passing
such longer running interaction work off
to worker threads not constraining the
availability of your system overall this
is one of the greatest shortcomings of
the servlet world kind of one pool for
all HTTP servlet requests if some of
them block against data stores they are
not available to
incoming requests anymore even if those
incoming requests could be perfectly
handled in a very efficient way with
cached responses returned
so you basically sacrifice the
availability and responsiveness of your
system if you target data stores lock in
some form so it is unfortunately from my
perspective a consequence of a truly
reactive architecture that the direction
with your data stores needs to be
rethought as well
you cannot just talk to your relational
database as you used to and transactions
the notion of a kind of longer running
interaction with a data store can be
translated into some degree but
consistency guarantees while you're
asking your data store to basically
create locks on tables and rows for you
is exactly what we're trying to avoid
here because the next thread is just
going to come along and have to wait for
that lock to be released which isn't any
better than waiting for a thread pool to
release a threat to you
my own perspective on it is that it's if
you really want to do reactive do it all
the way through down to the data store
level listening to it to what you said
it seems that the most important reason
for doing reactive programming is well
efficiency and performance and these
kinds of things so what you agree or is
there any other reason why you would do
it it is the primary reason I mean with
the consequences of improving the
availability and responsiveness of your
system because the runtime arrangement
can always provide has always has
threatening resources available for
upcoming requests in some form allowing
the architecture to differentiate
between requests that are very easy to
satisfy and others that are more
demanding if you're waiting for a data
store while basically you're waiting
your thread is being released back to
the pool in order to serve somebody
else's incoming a request which might be
much more efficient to create a response
for so in given that both in the JVM
world and in kind of operating systems
in general we have limitations on the
resources available you can't just have
an arbitrary number of threads you have
to live with a some limit being imposed
on you terms of the number of threads so
in particular for a
occasions with highly concurrent loads
there is no other way to scale them
without sacrificing availability and
responsiveness other than going reactive
at some point not not every application
falls into that category obviously but
quite a few applications or certain
parts of common applications out there
the public facing ones openly accessible
without any login or authentication
where anybody can send any number of
requests at any time to the to those
facades those are basically the parts of
a system that would benefit most
informational systems user facing
systems and of course systems with just
a very high number of users in general
what I see obviously you're working on
reactor Springs so why did you start
that project our reactive efforts have
actually started quite a while back
there were several factors involved
there was an interest but of course in
the team in general we were very very
aware of what was going on already in
ours javelins and kind of admirers of
some of some other efforts in the jvm
space and in the reactive angle in terms
of our own efforts we have been asked we
we actually or we reach out to people
and they turned out in conversations
that people are facing d constraints
resource constraints in in some parts of
the systems so some of those
conversations turned pretty concrete
people were already doing rxjava in
spring so there are already spring apps
out there as we speak here doing
reactive in spring writing in the spring
context in a spring application
environment using Eric's job on some of
them even using our own reactor effort
but basically in a handcrafted style
without any first-class support from the
framework itself some of those
discussions led to very concrete
suggestions that there could be
first-class reactive support in quite a
few parts of the Spring ecosystem
starting from the core framework where
some of the co-op's directions that we
have kind of at the moment are make
assumptions about how they are being
used the use of blocking input and
output streams and the use of read
locals the reactive spin leads to
variants of some of the
abstraction said immoral openly designed
towards a callback style towards back
pressure towards the non use of locals
and so this turned out from from a
couple of those corners into an effort
where we thought like alright let's do
some R&D here let's see what a spring
web endpoint model basically spring MVC
like model could look like with a
reactive engine underneath using some of
those newly created abstractions
underneath using their reactive streams
api's as kind of a foundation for the
interaction model and just seeing what
it feels like kind of spring MVC
unreactive so you mentioned rxjava quite
a few times can you say well if you
words about what that is and how it
relates to spring her extravagant in
java well it was largely developed at
netflix actually originated as part of a
larger effort with several language
bindings but the arocs Java has a has an
established role as a common library it
is already a little bit dated in the
meantime since it actually predates
reactive streams so the reactive streams
effort which is a collaboration between
several industry stakeholders created a
very minimal set of interfaces that we
called your reactive streams API and
Eric's Java to this day is not based on
reactive streams it just has reactive
streams adapters so it's it is a kind of
early generation programming library but
it is the common reference out there and
in our reactive spring efforts in our
initial goals and actually to this day
we aim to support our extravasated for
the user declared application endpoints
the arch travel observable type the RX
Java single type can be used in in the
endpoint signatures but as we move
forward with this there are more modern
minded alternatives to the arch Java
types
coming for example from our own reactor
project what are the features are of
extra value mentioned observables so
obviously it has to have some callback
mechanism it's most importantly T say a
composition library
it has a ton really a ton of composition
operators unobservable where you can
combine the outcome of one of your
callback operations with the with other
operations you can create whole
sequences of processing steps that
consume each other's output chains of
processing that are fed to an underlying
runtime and we're just a whole sequence
of callbacks produces the outcome in the
end observable is actually a huge a huge
piece of API you to composition methods
to all those operators reactor is kind
of coming from a similar angle the
reactor flux type and monotype are sort
of similar to observable and mono so
they are kind of arc Java rethought from
a reactive streams based perspective and
a little bit more focused set of
operators that are sufficient for the
eighty ninety percent use case but in
Indian direct Java is an admirable
effort in when it started and what it
did since we just believe that for a
forward-looking perspective rx Java 2 is
really highly anticipated they have a
plan for xj / - these intensity is
intended to be based on reactive streams
as well just didn't really make any
concrete progress yet or much concrete
progress yet so our reactor project to
this day is the most advanced reactive
stream spaced composition library out
there so reactor is actually a project
that is run by pivotal just like spring
indeed it is a an independently minded
effort on project red reactor dot-org
but they're very aligned with what
spring is doing it is used by quite a
few projects within the spring ecosystem
and within the wider pivotal portfolio
as well and it is our focus our kind of
preferred composition library for the
purposes in the reactive Spring
programming model we expect a reactor 3
though
released to go with Spring Framework 5
next year so it is very aligned in that
perspective so you mentioned reactive
streams so can you say something about
that how does it relate to reactor and
RX travel what is it what features does
provide reactive streams is more of a an
integrational effort then it's not
really user facing a very minimal set of
interfaces with a publisher subscriber a
subscription type allowing to interact a
publisher in the subscriber with some
basic means of back pressure where a
subscriber actually requests further
pieces of data from a publisher and the
publisher only really starts generating
them on demand as a subscriber is able
to to handle them to actually digest
them so it focuses on a particularly
important part of react different
direction the idea being that those
pieces come from different angles
different vendors the application level
pieces data store drivers web framework
endpoints interact through those common
abstractions provided by reactive
streams so it is a Neff with much larger
than reactive Spring we are working with
quite a few of the stakeholders in the
reactive stream space both the other
both other framework vendors but in
particular web server implementers and
data store companies so if for example
Couchbase there's even the Postgres
effort in that direction there's quite a
bit going on where the vendors
themselves would provide reactive
streams enabled data store drivers just
naturally allowing for being composed
into processing chains that are based on
the reactive streams API and the the
overall promise of our reactive spring
efforts actually rely on this happening
the the we cannot just solve their
reactive streams chal directive
programming challenges on our own we can
only really solve them in collaboration
with the teams behind say tomcat jetty
undertow nettie in particular but also
the data store drivers over there
for example Couchbase and others
we'll react if spring be based on Eric's
Java and reactor and reactive streams
therefore you're aiming for let me let
me find you in the wording it goes in
that direction of course but it is based
on reactive streams very fundamentally
the oak not reactive streams api's are
at literally at the heart of our
abstractions so they are the foundation
that we build on our user programming
model
the spring MVC like reactive weapon
point model supports Eric's Java in the
user level signatures so we don't
internally use our Java there we
understand user signatures physically
the application programmer using rxjava
in the callback signatures and naturally
bind to it so we 0 and rx Java
observable underneath the covers we are
reactive streams based using reactor as
our internal composition library so we
understand out isn't observable and we
can adapt to it we can interact with our
extravagant api's as the user chooses to
use them so we are not Irish tava based
the idea idea is that when the prototype
has first class support for rx Java as a
user level choice of ap is in the
callback signatures and reactor would
just be internal or is it also something
that I could use or should use on the
user level initially reactor was
primarily used for our own purposes
eternally we need to have some
composition library to to implement the
reactive web stack on a on our own end
however in the meantime with the effort
that is currently reacted to the drive
and moving to was a reactor 3 at O
reactor has flux and monitors that are
those two primary pieces of API that are
very very suitable for user level use
they are basically direct equivalents of
the common knowledge Java observable and
signal types and we are still in late
R&D early product decision stages here
but my current prediction is that the
primary user level choice for newly
started code will actually be the
reactor types in the end we will also
support our extravagance ouch number two
as it happens but I I see rxjava one is
more of a transitionary
for for newly started code in 2017 and
onwards it's probably going to be
reactor or possibly rxjava - as it as it
matures there are other programming
models for reactive applications so for
example there are actors how does what
you want to do in reactive Spring how
does that relate to actors actors are
fundamentally a different a different
architectural approach towards the same
problem space from from my perspective I
have a quite a long history kind of
looking with a dark current also
spending a bit of time with the people
behind us I guess a fine piece of
engineering the actor model is a
fundamental choice that they made at
some point initially and it seems to be
attractive to a certain architectural
mindset for sure from our own
perspective this is basically a fine
choice if it it fits your purposes but
from our own perspective we focus on a
more traditional style more spring
oriented style in the end where your
reactive web endpoint would be a spring
controller class a spring controller
type with at request mapping callback
methods the difference is almost only
noticeable when you when you look closer
the signatures of those handler methods
don't expect a pre bound object the pre
converted payload as an incoming
argument and they don't return a fully
computed response output at the end they
rather have an incoming arcs travel
observable for example or a reactor flux
and they happen to return an observable
or flux they basically are designed to
interact with a hot stream and an
incoming stream that has not been fully
processed yet and an outgoing stream
that is being processed with callbacks
coming in as we are able to write
further further data to the to the
servlet output or to the HTTP container
output yet adaptability of that model is
one of the sweet spots because we can
adapt it to a server 3 that one with
that one ace extreme world it just isn't
as efficient as it could be the same
model exactly the same programming model
also be run on a say Nettie runtime
underneath with the full level the full
exploit of of the efficiency that you
can possibly get from the model so we
are designing a programming model in a
way where it can be run on several
engines with a certain focus on Nettie
immediately it's just the common joys
out there for highly efficient network
stacks but also with the ability to run
on a servlet in the server container
world even on standards over 3.1
containers but we have an effort going
on where we are spend time with the
Tomcat guys and the jetty guys creating
more efficient ways of interacting with
a servlet based container there's a
reactive streams Commons effort reactive
straight towards towards a servlet
bridge where we can obtain efficient
handles from a given service request
allowing us to interact with it through
the reactive streams ApS so there's
quite a bit of interesting collaboration
going on your industry collaboration
going on here trying to avoid artificial
barriers for efficient processing
allowing us and others to provide common
programming model elements come in a
common programming model style without
making assumptions about the particular
random in the sense of oh I'm bound on
to Nettie or I'm bound to jetty or
Tomcats binding here a common reactively
oriented programming model for weapon
points that can be adapted to those
several engines underneath the covers so
we're basically back to a very spring
oriented perspective there is a little
bit of deployment abstraction going on
here of designing your application
components once and being able to reuse
them in different kinds of deployment
arrangements so we're basically back to
a very spring original spring promise
for the purposes of reactive programming
here how would that be different if you
would be using actors regs architectural
is just a very unique style
it's basically a message passing model
with actors being able to hold state for
you
you can kind of have an actual like
arrangement with spring as well I'm sure
actually some people do this in some
form
but the way that we are looking at it is
we don't see actors as a kind of as an
option that's particularly attractive to
the mainstream
we are very mainstream focused in a
positive sense
we intend to whatever we do basically we
aim to do it in a way that at least can
be attractive to a wide range of
developers in particular enterprise
developers out there my own experiences
and also the experiences from others
I've been talking to is that the actor
model is kind of a it is attractive to a
particular corner of the space two
particular architectures two particular
processing architectures where message
passing is just a natural way of
interacting between the components of
your system to begin with where it fits
basically your architectural
understanding of your own system but it
is not necessarily an ideal match for
where most people come from in terms of
the spring audience or the wider Java
Enterprise audience many of them do rest
rest and direction with chasing payloads
or custom pedals some of them do
messaging on WebSockets for example so
particular messaging styles but not
really act a message passing but more
like message protocol payloads on the
WebSocket channel bound to WebSocket
resources so we know where people come
from and in terms of our own reactive
efforts we want to take them where they
are
so basically keep being focused on rest
endpoint architectures rest payload
processing just in your reactive style
we are not trying to kind of turn them
into a completely different
architectural model we allow them to
rethink the architecture obviously but
the idea is that you actually preserve a
lot of the architectural investment that
you already have or the architecture
understanding of your own system that
you already have and you start using
reactive programming model measures
reactive programming model elements in
your architecture to solve particular
hotspot problems that you may already
have or that you expect to be having as
a kind of defensive measure particularly
nice fit with a micro-services
architecture where some of the micro
services would particularly benefit from
a reactive approach whereas others may
be just happy the way they are and keep
being happy for years to come
the way in a traditional more
traditionally architected way there's
nothing wrong with that from our
perspective we've been talking already
about what it means for developers so
you were talking about how there is a
different model for spring and we see
for the the traditional web framework is
reactive spring only for web
applications it is as our initial goal
that we're working towards it is very
focused on web and print processing
however it is by no means exclusively
designed for it we spend a lot of time
actually rethinking our lower level
abstractions so resources reaction
stream abstractions that are perfectly
applicable to non web scenarios as kind
of a second step we have our own
messaging abstractions already we have a
quite an audience out there doing
message oriented architectures with
spring and reactive programming model
elements coming in there may be just as
highly demanded as for us for the web
but our initial stakeholders so the the
people that we've been talking to early
adopters people expressing an
interesting in the early adoption here
they are primarily interested in
efficient HTTP endpoint processing so
it's a very pragmatic choice for us to
initially focus on it the wider effort
in the longer spring 5/3 X evolution
will just have other first class and
areas in mind that we are applying the
same principles to very much again in an
inner spring a spring mindset where we
reuse stylistic elements across
different endpoint models which is going
to do the same here as people who would
expect us to so you already said that
the model will be very much like the old
model where you have at request mapping
to entertain methods certain HTTP
requests and you will just have
different signature is that it is that
how the model is different or are there
any more details that are different
let's just clarify to avoid the
misunderstanding that we're reusing
stylistic elements from our programming
model so this is not running on the same
engine a spring MVC and it does not have
the full set of identical capabilities
it reuses a lot of the common elements
its controller classes we
instant state requests mapping for the
for the for the bindings to methods
there are quite a few common things you
can express your quest piping signatures
that you can also use in traditional
spring servlet mu C but there are all
the limitations to what you can do
say JSP rendering it just does not make
any sense in a in a reactive weapon
point model so you know that you're
working with reactive weapon points
you're not working with an abstract
model you're working with a reactive web
endpoint model that is kind of makes an
common stylistic impression because it
reuses stylistic elements that you know
from traditional spring MVC and other
spring endpoint models but you know that
you're working with the reactive engine
with certain constraints in mind certain
things you can do here that you couldn't
do in spring MSE and the other way
around
it's also technically two different
stacks so even in spring five there's
going to be a traditional spring servlet
MVC stack which is pretty much it is an
evolution of what we have now but it is
its own little its own little thing
we're not going away from the power of
the server model and the power of the
existing server based libraries out
there you can't keep doing what you're
doing on spring so every time we see
without any compromises in parallel to
that there's a reactive web stack that's
kind of independent both code base wise
and in terms of its runtime
characteristics they really come
together at the top end at the
programming model level that's where the
commonalities appear again so we're
doing this with a particular vision that
we have in mind here and we're going to
have to have quite a few tutorials
nicely arranged documentation pieces
that that are just illustrating both the
common parts between those worlds and
the strong differences in particular in
terms of runtime assumptions that you
can make I think I will also add the
guides the spring guides to to the links
for the show because they they are
really nice to get some hands-on
experience with spring technologies so
why can't you do tree is P rendering and
reactive application well for a start
there's not necessarily self-contained
underneath in contrast to spring every
10 BC the simulate API does not like I
mentioned before that we can adapt the
spring reactive web and print model onto
so every 3.1 containers but the servlet
model does never shine through we are
not making any assumptions about several
characteristics JSP strongly tied to
service so there's no way to go without
you will be able to rent the templates
so like trigger a free market or a
family if render step at the moment
that's a blocking operation because the
template engines don't really allow us
to direct with them in in a back
pressure driven way but there's still
some some way to go and as we evolve
with this I'm sure there will be like
from a family that were even free market
there will be ways of talking to them in
a more reactively minded style in a
non-blocking style called the driven
style so i we see those pieces coming
together but even initially if your
template rendering step is very
efficient you're only blocking for a
very short period in the end if the
payload is not too large there might not
be that much negative effect to begin
with this this is really part of where a
reactive web application will differ
from a traditionally minded one you're
going to be very focused on also the
size of your payloads and whether they
even worth decomposing whereas
traditional well JSP or a template based
apps they often just render enormously
long responses out without even worrying
and so the we are we are aiming for a
balance here where people have to be
very aware of what they're doing in the
reactive world to actually get the
benefits it is way too easy to code sort
of reactively and not actually get too
much benefit out of it and that's that's
a bad compromise you have because you
are actually spending a lot of of energy
rethinking your architecture adapting to
the reactive mindset coding in a
different way you're giving up on quite
a few things
starting from longer running transaction
boundaries and that sort of thing you
want to get some benefits out of it so
the worst possible scenario is doing it
in a kind of half-baked fashion so we're
really trying to do it in a way where we
wear spring MVC traditional server day
then we see remains attractive to an
audience wanting those benefits that
compromise that style my own perspective
is that in years
to come a lot of new code will be
written with the traditional spring MVC
model drew traditionally Springs of it
based MVC model there's nothing wrong
with that as mentioned in the micro
services world you may choose to use the
reactive end point style in some of your
micro services but not in others maybe
80% are traditionally coded and 20% are
reactively architected would it make
sense to pod over a servlet base spring
MVC application to the new model from
with that perspective in mind that we've
just been talking about I would argue
towards no I would not just port it if
you want to react attacked a particular
web and point arrangement a particular
micro service that you have if you want
to react attack the towards a reactive
arrangement that's not really a port
it's a kind of react attacking of the
entire service as part of that you may
also recall your web layer towards the
reactive spring web style that's
perfectly fine porting suggests that you
basically take the code and with very
little measures you've got something
that delivers benefits in the other
world and it's not quite like that you
could try to do it for rest very rest
oriented architectures you could try to
do it but if everything else remains the
same in particular your data store
interaction remains the same you might
not get as much benefit out of it as you
would think so in that sense you might
be better off keeping it a traditional
way until you actually have a problem
actual demand that suggests that a
reactive rethinking of the entire
service will deliver significant
benefits and that's when when you should
touch your weapon points you said that
one of the reasons why you would use the
new model is basically performance and
scalability and so on when would you
rather use the old spring MVC model even
in new applications in the future well
in services in certain parts of an
application where where your web
interaction is not a bottleneck you
won't get much benefit out of reactive
web interaction model since it's simply
not the bottleneck right if if your rep
requests just go in go to a JPA layer
underneath and spend a lot of time
talking to your database and a lot of
CPU cycles on translating the results of
the database back to objects if that's
where your bottleneck is I'd rather
spend the time we are connecting that
of the system the data store part of the
system whereas if you know that your hot
spots are actually in at the web layer
you may of course touch it selectively
even there but say a lot of enterprise
applications are more traditionally
structured traditionally architected
crud applications with object relational
mapping underneath for those kinds of
services you're probably better off just
keeping them on the Supreme Soviet
embassy model or even if new services
are being created the architecting them
on that model as long as the rest of the
architecture further down the call stack
is equally traditional there's nothing
wrong with that at all it is a very
consistent arrangement American system
binds that then and in terms of
transaction scopes and everything else
so it actually is a benefit overall I'm
very much a believer that a particular
service or a particular part of an
application needs to make architectural
sense wholesale from top to bottom so we
already spoke about how some databases
are supporting reactive streams however
if I look at JDBC that's obviously a
blocking model so what about non
blocking JDBC is that something that we
can be looking forward it is something
that we can hope for being being
invested in in about by more
stakeholders the one effort that I'm
familiar with somewhat familiar with is
in post grassland where it's not really
truly PC based so it's kind of a an
alternative java database driver
reactively minded we are going to see
more of those efforts for sure for
databases where the backend the DBMS
itself and the network protocol actually
allow for reactive implementation style
so it's very dependent on whether the
back-end of the database can actually
efficiently satisfy our reactive demands
and the backpressure oriented
interaction but we're going to see some
of this unfortunately from my own
perspective it's not just the driver
style in a relational traditionally
minded relational database world you
also have strong transaction assumptions
in there you expect rows to be locked
for you with certain isolation levels
there's that quite a lot of elements in
the reactive India in the relational
database world there are not an ideal
fit
or a reactive datastore indirection
model there is a demo somewhere and I
think the databases that you're
supporting there are couchdb Postgres
and that's it or is there anyone else
anything else there quite a few ongoing
efforts this is also actually a
particular thread of our thinking here
is we want to do things at the right
time we don't want to be too early where
nobody else basically has reactive
streams efforts ready we hope that by
next year which is our spring from a5
kind of GA target 2017 first half of
2017 by that time I hope that more of
those efforts actually reach GA status
or at least very close to it where it
just becomes a more attractive model
overall what about other technologies I
mean for example there's JPA the object
relational weapon in the in the Java
space and that is as far as I know based
on JDBC so you can't do JPA and a
reactive application yes it is based on
JDBC for a start but it's also even
strong in terms of its transactional
assumptions and if you want to make any
modifications to your model being
written back to the data store you have
to do them within a transaction scope
you have to load the objects within the
same scope that you're modifying them in
or you have to merge them back in so
it's it's almost by design not meant to
be used for like very short efficient
interactions with your target datastore
it's more meant for a servlet oriented
model where you basically take in
request you know the entire amount of
changes that you want to do you start a
JP a transaction you load all the
objects that need to be modified you
it's only really efficient if you do all
the operations within combined
transactions a little bit longer lived
for that reason so in your transitionary
phase in particular or in just in
architectures where only some of the
requests actually go down to the
datastore level to begin with it may be
perfectly alright if some of those
requests then just do GA PA as blocking
operations and return in a very crud
oriented system where almost all the
requests go down to the JPA level I
would argue it's not a great fit if you
want to do a reactively oriented web
architecture on top of it you're not
going to be happy with the outcome
what about HTTP to
the impact of http/2 on spring spring
MBC and the whole framework I tend to
actually refer to HTTP 2 quite often in
particular with a as a theme for spring
5 in its own right well I admit it's
actually more of an ongoing theme
already We strongly believe and I
personally strongly believe that we need
to embrace HTTP 2 there's no way we can
just keep doing things the traditional
way in Java land without at least going
HTTP 2 for you for a start so all the
servlet containers all our simulate
based architectures need at least need
to make the move towards a cheap HTTP 2
for a start in particular in order to
allow the container to do the best
possible job given the service model
because it works quite nicely
the impact on developers on application
developers is actually not too strong
HTTP to support in the servant world is
largely transparent to the application
it is a change in terms of the service
own architecture it is a change in terms
of the configuration style for the
server to some degree but the
application compounds themselves they
can keep receiving servlet oriented
requests as they are used to so it is a
very straightforward step to take
upgrade to JD 93 or Tomcat 8 or 5 or 1 0
1 or 3 or higher configured them to use
HTTP 2 underneath the covers which is
not entirely trivial but it's basically
an effort you should be willing to go
through and then just deploy your
existing applications on top of it if
the rest of your IT infrastructures are
unlike your proxies and so forth are
also HTTP 2 capable you might actually
benefit from it should be - very quickly
without having to touch your application
code much so it's it's almost the
inverse situation from the reactive
programming benefits where with reactive
programming you have to react attacked
your code in order to get the benefits
with HTTP 2 you can't leave your code as
it is and through configuration and
infrastructure updates yet almost all of
the benefits so in that sense it's a
no-brainer and this is really a call out
to to everybody with existing spring web
applications out there please consider
the HTTP 2 enabled options tanka dated
529 to 3 in particular so Spri active
spring is probably one of the major new
features in spring 5
what answers plan for spring five one of
our original themes for spring five was
JDK nine it still is but it's certainly
been a little de-emphasized compared to
the reactive theme so in terms of the
programming model impact our reactive
programming model efforts and the
underlying abstractions the reactive
streams alignment the preparations for
spring data reactive stream support in
the years mediator repository model all
of those things affect the back into the
core framework the core framework needs
to enable all of this so this is our
widest broadest and deepest theme but
just next up is JDK 9 now's basically in
number two now in the theme list not
number one anymore
is JDK 9 in there are quite a few nice
things we can do with JDK 9 currently
like JDK 9 actually is the first GDK to
ship and http2 enabled web stack
out-of-the-box as opposed to the LPN
protocol and http2 enabled alternative
to the good old URL connection client so
we're going to embrace all of this for
spring applications running on JDK 9
more importantly we see ourselves
recommending the use of spring fanchetti
can learn quite a bit for the JVM level
benefits compact strings the revisions
to the g1 garbage collector there are a
lot of really nice improvements to the
runtime in in JDK 9 that spring
applications in particular microservices
oriented one epic oriented applications
are going to benefit from very
immediately so even without using any of
the programming level features in JD
King line there are going to be a lot of
benefits to deploying a spring 5
application on JDK 9 so it is an
important theme we are still tracking
our efforts towards jigsaw the module
system but at the moment chicks are is
not an ideal fit for our vision of what
a configuration story needs to look like
so we're not actually focusing on jigsaw
at the moment well timeline wise at this
point it looks like spring from ik 5
will actually become generally available
before JDK 9 but we have had that
situation before with spring fall and
JDK 8 we're going to ship best effort
early support for JDK 9 we will
basically go GA first and just declare
the JDK not support not production
yet but we are likely to build on JDK
nine already and you will be able to use
spring five on JDK nine Release
Candidate builds at that point so
there's nothing there's nothing wrong
with the timelines not matching from my
perspective it is still an important
theme well HTTP 2 we already discussed
this kind of a an ongoing theme that has
a connection to servlet for the dough
template for the dough unfortunately
doesn't really make as much progress as
we would like it to but if he starts
moving forward again towards a tomcat 9
being based on that and so forth we will
also embrace her late for the dough to
the best possible degree a couple of
other ideas towards alternative
configuration styles in spring so that's
there's quite a lot of thinking of what
we consider doing but since we're not
even in the milestone phase yet there
haven't been any hard decisions outside
of the key themes so there will be the
reactive story there will be early gdk9
support there will be a strong HTTP to
focus as we're going through the
milestone phase we're going to see what
else makes it in okay thanks a lot
thanks a lot for the interview what's
very interesting thanks for having the
opportunity and let's see where
everything turns out so in the course of
this year I'm looking forward to it
myself
yeah thank you thanks for listening I
see radio an educational program brought
to you by I Triple E software magazine
for more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at SC - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group online
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at SES radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]